בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Today's דף daf *daf* ס"ד *Samech Dalet*, 64,
we are finishing the דרשות drashot *drashot* that was on the two
first דפים dappim *daphim* of מרובה Meruba *Meruba* about how we know
that you pay כפל kefel. *kefel* on all objects. There are two
cases in the תורה Torah *Torah*. There's the case here where it
basically starts by saying, כי יגנוב איש שור shor. או שה seh,
וטבחו או מכרו חמישה בקר ישלם תחת השור וארבע צאן תחת השה
*Ki yignov ish shor o seh utvacho o mecharo chamisha vakar yeshalem
tachat hashor ve'arba tzon tachat haseh*. So that's the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*
about שור shor או שה seh *shor o seh*. This is the
more straight פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* about the חיוב chiyuv *chiyuv* of a
גנב ganav? *ganav*. כי יגנוב איש שור shor, או שה seh, וטבחו
או מכרו חמישה בקר וארבע צאן *Ki yignov ish shor o seh
utvacho o mecharo chamisha
vakar ve’arba
tzon*. וארבע צאן *ve’arba tzon*, so that's the four and five. And
then it says, אם המצא תמצא בידו הגניבה im himatzei timatzei be-yado
ha-gneiva, משור עד חמור chamor, עד שה seh, חיים שנים ישלם chayim
shnayim yeshalem. *Im himatzei timatzei beyado hageneiva mishor ad chamor ad seh
chayim shnayim yeshalem*. He didn't sell it. משור עד חמור chamor עד
שה se חיים chayim. *mishor ad chamor ad seh chayim*. And since
that shows שור shor *shor* and חמור chamor, *chamor*, and they are
alive, they haven't been slaughtered, שנים ישלם shnayim yeshalem, *shnayim yeshalem*. So
that's the clear פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* about four and five if it's
slaughtered and sold or double if it's not. Then you got this
whole complicated thing in the context of a שומר shomer. *shomer*. You
gave something somebody to watch, it got stolen, if the גנב ganav
*ganav* is found he pays double, which is of course just referring
back to the idea that a גנב ganav *ganav* pays double. If
the גנב ganav. *ganav* isn't found and then there's some type of
court case, the guy could wind up paying double, and we said
that that's if he claims it was a גנב ganav *ganav* and
he stole it. So until now we've been focusing on this second
thing and looking at this case about him claiming that it was
stolen to learn out that גניבה gneiva. *geneiva* and כפל kefel *kefel*
applies by all these things. And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
let's go back actually to these פסוקים pesukim. *psukim* up here, which
is a classic פסוקים pesukim *psukim* by גניבה gneiva *geneiva* where it
says משור עד חמור chamor עד שה seh חיים chayim *mishor ad
chamor ad seh chayim*. It says this list of things and that'll
tell us that גניבה gneiva, *geneiva* applies, that כפל kefel *kefel* applies
to all things with the exception of course of things like land
and שטרות shtarot. *shtarot* etc. That's where we left off yesterday. So
let's take a look now as we pick up on ס"ד ע"א
*Samech Dalet Amud Aleph*.
Where's that first כי יגנוב איש שור shor או שה *Ki yignov
ish shor
o seh*?
I don't remember, it's somewhere in משפטים *Mishpatim*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. אמר מר יאמר שור shor וגניבה *Amar Mar: Yomar
shor ve-geneiva*. It's about thirteen lines down from the top of ס"ד
ע"א *Samech Dalet Amud Aleph*. Let's see if we can get even
a little more ahead. תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av* is coming
up, maybe we won't have, we can sort of skip it today.
אמר מר יאמר שור shor, וגניבה *Amar Mar: Yomar shor ve-geneiva*. Why
didn't it just say אם המצא תמצא בידו im himatzei timatzei be-yado.
הגניבה משור *Im himatzei timatzei beyado hageneiva mishor*? Why did it have
to say חמור chamor *chamor* and שה *seh* and חיים chayim *chayim*?
And that allowed it to expand to include everything. So that's the
phrase. Why didn't it just say שור shor, *shor* and גניבה gneiva
*geneiva*? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, מי כתיב שור shor
גניבה gneiva, גניבה gneiva שור shur דכתיב *Mi k'tiv shor geneiva? Geneiva
shor d'chtiv*, right? It says הגניבה משור *ha-geneiva mishor*. Now you could
think the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is being a little bit picky-yune, but
the point is, are we conceiving of it as a כלל ופרט
klal u-pratt *klal u-prat* or פרט pratt וכלל *prat u-klal*? If you
said that it said שור shur *shor* and גניבה gneiva, *geneiva* and
you end with the broader term גניבה gneiva *geneiva*, you're allowing it
to be an expansive category. But if you're saying, well why didn't
it just say גניבה gneiva ושור *geneiva ve-shor*, the answer is obvious.
Then it would have been a כלל ופרט klal u-prat *klal u-prat*
and it would have been limited to שור shur *shor*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says וכי תימא אילו נאמר קאמר *ve-chi teima ilu
ne'emar ka'amar*, maybe what the ברייתא braita *Braita* means is, had it
said, why couldn't it have said, אילו נאמר שור shur? וגניבה *ilu
ne'emar shor ve-geneiva*, had it said שור shur. *shor* and גניבה gneiva
*geneiva* in that order and ended with the broader term גניבה gneiva?
*geneiva*, and been a כלל klal. *klal*, I would have then
included a broad category of things but not everything, maybe only things
that are offered as sacrifices. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one
minute, וממי מצית אמרת *u-mi matzes amart*? But then if it had
been written that way, שור *shor* and then גניבה gneiva, *geneiva*, how
could you have said מה פרט מפורש mah pratt meforash... *ma prat
meforash*, the פרט pratt. *prat* is something that a שור *shor* is
something that's a קרבן *korban*, I would have included all of the
קרבן *korban*. That's a classic thing to say, similar to the פרט
pratt. *prat* when you've got a כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-klal
*klal prat u-klal*. But if you only have the word שור *shor*
and גניבה gneiva *geneiva*, you only have two options. Either a כלל
ופרט klal u'prat *klal u-prat*, so you only have the שור *shor*,
or פרט pratt? וכלל *prat u-klal* and you have everything. And the
ברייתא braita. *Braita* is dealing with the assumption that had some of
these words been written, you would have had a כלל פרט וכלל
klal prat u-klal, *klal prat u-klal*. You would have had an expansion
of the פרט pratt, *prat*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says how
would that have worked out? וממי מצית אמרת מה פרט מפורש Ma
prat m'forash, הוי שור פרט pratt וגניבה כלל פרט וכלל klal prat
u-klal נעשה כלל klal? מוסיף על הפרט *U-mi matzes amart ma prat
meforash havei shor prat ve-geneiva klal prat u-klal na'asa klal mosif al
ha-prat*. The כלל klal, *klal* adds to the פרט pratt, *prat* וישתרבו
לכל מילי *ve-yishteravu le-chol mili* and it would have included everything. So
what's the ברייתא braita *Braita*'s assumption that with some of these words
I would have expanded the concrete cases? Where's the כלל פרט וכלל
klal prat u-klal, *klal prat u-klal* to be working like that?
You say, well isn't it everything? In other words, if it's alive,
גניבה gneiva. חיים chayim *geneiva chayim*, and I couldn't have just said
that?
So you're saying חיים chayim *chayim* is the כלל klal. *klal*, but
the ברייתא Braita *Braita* didn't say that. So let's see where the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gets to. אלא Ella... כי דכתיב קאמר
*Ella ki d'chtiv ka-ami*. Fine. The ברייתא braisa, *Braita* is saying had
it been written in the order it
said, גניבה gneiva ושור *geneiva ve-shor*. But you still got the problem.
Why would that have led to an expansion of the category? וממי
מצית אמרת הכל בכלל *u-mi matzes amart hakol biklal*? How could you
have said that, oh that would have been very inclusive, ומה פרט
prat מפורש *ve-ma prat meforash* and
or we'll go by something similar to the פרט prat *prat*, we'll
go by a קרבן *korban*. If you have the כלל klal ופרט
*klal u-prat*... If you have the כלל klal and פרט prat. order,
you're even worse, then you're just limited to the פרט. prat הוי
ליה גניבה כלל ושור פרט, כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט,
Havei lei Gneiva klal ve-shor pratt, klal u-pratt ein ba-klal ela mah
she-ba-pratt,
you'd be limited to the פרט. שור אין מילי אחריני לא, Shor
in mili achrini lo, only a שור.
So the גמרא Gemara says this whole ברייתא that sort of started
with this list and expanded it to include everything similar to that
list, right, that assumes a כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-pratt u-klal structure.
But where's the כלל ופרט וכלל? klal u-pratt u-klal? We only have
the word גניבה. gneiva Okay. So Michael has said חיים. chayim, Maybe
that's serving as a כלל. klal What else could you have said
is the כלל? klal שניים ישלם, Shnayim yeshallem,
which is not exactly a כלל, klal but okay, since it just
says you pay double, we'll treat that to mean everything. So that's
where the גמרא's Gemara, going to go. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר
רבא תנא החיים קסמיך. Amar Rava tanna hachayim kasameich. Ah, the תנא's
tanna just using the word חיים chayim. to be the final
כלל. klal. Okay. וכלל ופרט וכלל קאמר ליה. Ve-klal u-pratt u-klal ka'amar
lei. It is a כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-pratt u-klal. כלל ופרט
וכלל, Klal u-pratt u-klal, you
know, it's גניבה gneivah, is anything, חיים chayim is sort of anything,
anything that's alive, and these are the פרטים. prattim. And that's why
it would have expanded it. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
ואלא לא דמי כללא בתרא לכללא קמא? Ve-ala lo dami klala batra
le-klala kamma?
The final כלל klal. is not similar to the opening כלל klal,
because the opening כלל klal, really is everything, גניבה, gneivah? and the
final כלל klal is a smaller group of things, living things. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, הא תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל הוא. Ha
tanna de-vei Rabbi Yishmael hu. This is the תנא tanna from the
house of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, דכי האי גוונא דרשי כללי ופרטי,
de-chi hai gavna darshi klalei u-prattei,
that that works for כלל klal ופרט even if the final כלל
klal, is a smaller group than the opening כלל. klal, והכי קקשיא
ליה. Ve-hachi ka-kashya lei. And
here's how you read the ברייתא. אם המצא תמצא למה לי? Im
himatzei timatzei lamma li?
Why do you need אם המצא im himatzei, תמצא בידו b'yado הגניבה,
which is like a broad statement? I heard it's read as a
type of a כלל. klal, אם בידו הגניבה Im be-yado ha-gneiva or
something. יאמר שור וגניבה וחיים. Yomar shor ve-gneiva ve-chayim.
Say, okay, so this is going to be the כלל ופרט וכלל.
klal u-pratt u-klal. I need another color. This is the... this is
the כלל, klal this is the כלל, klal okay, and these are
the פרטים. prattim. So המצא תמצא himatzei timatzei is seen as being
very broad. So it says, why do you need המצא תמצא? himatzei
timatzei? If you have a כלל klal and a... two כללים klalim
and one of these פרטים, prattim, let that expand and include everything.
And then we're going to say, no, these פרטים prattim by themselves
would not have given you everything. And that's why you needed המצא
תמצא himatzei timatzei to be more inclusive. Okay.
Why do you need the פרט? Why not just say המצא תמצא
בידו הגניבה? himatzei timatzei be-yado ha-gneiva?
Well, because we have to exclude things like קרקע ושטרוס karka ve-shtaros
and so on. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, והכי
קקשיא ליה אם המצא תמצא למה לי? Ve-hachi ka-kashya lei im himatzei
timatzei lamma li?
Why did I need המצא תמצא? himatzei timatzei? יאמר שור וגניבה וחיים.
Yomar shor ve-gneiva ve-chayim.
Say
שור which is the פרט, גניבה וחיים gneiva ve-chayim which are the
כללים, klalim, והכל בכלל, ve-ha-kol be-chol,
and include everything. אילו כן. Ilu kein. Now we're just going to
re-read the ברייתא with this understanding that the חיים chayim is the
other כלל klal and המצא תמצא himatzei timatzei is something that comes
in at the end to make it even more broad. Okay. אילו
כן הייתי אומר. Ilu kein hayiti omer. No, מה פרט מפורש דבר
הקרב גבי מזבח. mah pratt meforash davar ha-karev gabbei mizbe'ach.
If it had just said שור, I would have limited it to
things that could be brought as sacrifices. אף כל הקרב גבי מזבח.
Af kol ha-karev gabbei mizbe'ach. מה יש לך להביא? Mah yesh le-cha
le-havi?
What would have been included beyond שור that could be brought as
a sacrifice? שה, a sheep. כשהוא אומר שה, Keshe-hu omer seh, but
then it says sheep. So clearly that's meant to expand it even
further. הרי זה שה אמור. Harei zeh seh amur. So we have
a sheep said. מה אני מקיים גניבה? Mah ani mekayyem gneiva?
So what's the point now of the כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-pratt
u-klal if you have both שור and שה said? לרבות כל דבר.
Lerabbos kol davar. Must be to come to include everything.
Okay, but one minute, so if that's true, יאמר גניבה, yomar gneiva,
why did you need the other stuff in the פסוק? pasuk? יאמר
גניבה
ושור ושה וחיים. Yomar gneiva ve-shor ve-seh ve-chayim. Just say גניבה's gneivah.
the כלל, klal, שור ושה's shor ve-seh the פרט and חיים chayim,
is the כלל, klal והכל בכלל, ve-ha-kol be-chol, and I would include
everything. So why did I need the other things of the פסוק?
pasuk No, אילו כן, ilu kein, I wouldn't have included anything. Had
it just said that, הייתי אומר, hayiti omer, I would have said,
מה פרט מפורש דבר הקדוש בבכורה. mah pratt meforash davar ha-kadosh bi-vechora.
That I would have limited שור and שה, an ox and a
sheep, to things that are sanctified with the firstborn. אף כל דבר
הקדוש בבכורה. Af kol davar ha-kadosh bi-vechora.
And so that's what's meant to expand to, to include also donkeys.
So that's... so and if that's true, so... ממילא mimmela I wouldn't
have included everything in the universe. I would have said שור ושה,
shor ve-seh, כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-pratt u-klal only gave me donkeys
as well. So מה יש לך להביא? mah yesh le-cha le-havi? So
what would that then have included? חמור, donkey. כשהוא אומר חמור, Keshe-hu
omer chamor, but then it says donkey. הרי חמור אמור. Harei chamor
amur. מה אני מקיים גניבה? Mah ani mekayyem gneiva? So now I've
got a כלל, klal, you know, גניבה, gneivah, שור שה וחמור shor
seh ve-chamor is the פרט,
and then another כלל חיים. klal chayim. So what is being included
by, you know, by the כלל ופרט וכלל? klal u-pratt u-klal? It's
not just sacrifices, it's not just things קדוש בבכורה, kadosh bi-vechora, that's
explicit in the פסוק. pasuk So what's being included by the כלל
ופרט וכלל? klal u-pratt u-klal? It must be לרבות כל דבר. lerabbos
kol davar. Now that I've got both all the שור, the שה,
and the חמור and the כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u-pratt u-klal, must
be I'm including everything. Okay, so now is my question, why did
I need the other stuff
in the פסוק? pasuk יאמר גניבה ושור ושה וחמור וחיים Yomar gneiva
ve-shor ve-seh ve-chamor ve-chayim והכל בכלל. ve-ha-kol be-chol. That would have included
everything. Why did I also need it to say המצא תמצא? himatzei
timatzei? That's the implicit question. No, אילו כן, ilu kein, had I
just stopped there with that כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u-pratt u-klal, הייתי
אומר, hayiti omer, I would have said, מה פרט מפורש... No, that
wouldn't have included everything. שור, חמור, and שה you abstract it, you
don't get all things, you just get animals. אף כל בעלי חיים,
af kol baalei chayim, limited to animals. מה יש לך להביא, mah
yesh lecha lehavi,
and therefore what do I still need to include? שאר בעלי חיים,
sh'ar baalei chayim, other animals. Ah, but why do I need the
כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-klal, to include other animals? תיהוי אומר
חיים הרי חיים אמור. tihvei omer chayim harei chayim amur.
This last כלל klal does double duty. This last כלל klal tells
you because it's a כלל klal, we're going to be expansive, but
so a little bit ironically it's going to have the effect of
expanding it beyond just animals. Because what it explicitly says is animals.
So functioning at the explicit level, it's including all animals. Functioning at
the כלל klal level, it's going beyond that. Because it can't just
be coming to include animals, because then it's not a כלל, klal
then just say חיים, chayim okay? So somehow because if you just
wanted to say animals, just say חיים. chayim But because you have
a כלל klal and a פרט and a כלל, klal. and this
כלל klal, is telling you both A we're already talking about animals
and B we're now going to expand it, it's going to tell
you to go beyond animals.
You don't need a כלל klal at all. So it's just telling
you the דין din has to be alive? I understand.
That's just the way the גמרא Gemara is interpreting, I cannot defend
this on a פשט pshat level.
המני מקיים גניבה hamanni mikayeim gneiva לרבות כל דבר. l'rabot kol davar.
So now you got the כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat u-klal so
the פרטים pratim sort of tell you animals because חיים is also
telling you animals, so the other effect of the כלל, klal actually
the גמרא Gemara says it better than I just did, because maybe
the כלל klal of חיים doesn't go beyond animals, but the כלל
klal of גניבה gneivah, now is going to go beyond animals and
it's going to go beyond these concrete cases. So that's the לרבות
כל דבר. l'rabot kol davar. So now we've got it. Because of
the כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-klal we have through this list,
I mean you could ask why need שור חמור ושה shor chamor
v'se if you could have just said חיים, but because of this
list, we've got animals, and it's a כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat
u-klal. and this כלל klal part should go beyond animals and include
everything. So now that we've included everything, who needs
המצא תמצא? himatzei timatzei? Okay. המצא
תמצא למה לי? himatzei timatzei lama li? And that's what the ברייתא
is saying. So now the גמרא's Gemara going to say, okay, that's
a good question. What's the answer? אי הכי i hachi says the
גמרא, Gemara, שפיר קשיא ליה, shapir kasha lei, it's got a good
answer, it's got a good question. If you've got everything included by
the כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat u-klal. who needs המצא תמצא? himatzei
timatzei? Now, here's the answer. Here's what you need it for. משום
דאיכא פירכא, mishum d'ika pircha, because that's got a challenge. לרבות כל
דבר מהיכא קמייתא לה l'rabot kol davar meheicha kamaisa la מכלל בתרא.
miklal batra. In order to include things beyond animals, you're using the
second כלל. klal Right, before the גמרא Gemara, said you were using
the first כלל, klal. גניבה, gneivah. but here they say, no, no,
no, it's the second כלל klal that does the broadening.
מכלל בתרא כללא גופיה חיים כתיב. miklal batra klal gufei chayim ketiv.
Okay, so
כלל פרט וכלל מאי כמהני ליה? klal prat u-klal mai kamahani lei?
So the גמרא Gemara is now pointing out the obvious problem. How
can you say that this כלל klal which is explicitly tells you
animals is coming to expand beyond animals? The כלל klal itself says
animals. Okay. אי לאסויי כל דבר הא חיים כתיב בעלי חיים אין
מידי אחריני לא. i la'asuyei kol davar ha chayim ketiv baalei chayim
in midi achrini lo. No, the גמרא Gemara says you cannot with
this כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-klallim, have gotten beyond animals. Because
remember, the כלל klal and פרט you're limited to the פרט. The
last כלל klal, is the one that expands. But if the last
כלל klal, says animals, how can you expand beyond animals? So with
this structure, you would have been limited to animals, and that's why
you needed המצא תמצא himatzei timatzei to go beyond animals. משום הכי
אצטריך אם המצא. mishum hachi hitztariach im himatzei. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara? says one minute. אמרי והא שני כללות סמיכי אהדדי
נינהו. amri v'ha shnei klalos smichi ahadadi ninhu. So המצא תמצא himatzei
timatzei is like a double כלל. Somehow these are seen as two
כלל words. אם המצא, himatzei if anything is found, each one of
these is like a כלל word. So the גמרא Gemara says if
there's two functioning as like these two כלל words by itself, how
does that like operate in conjunction with like everything else here? That
shouldn't normally do a normal type of כלל פרט וכלל klal prat
u'klal, function. It's just two כללין klallin standing there. So the גמרא's
gemara going to say, and the question isn't so obvious, the answer
makes it clear what the גמרא's gemara getting at. אמר רבינא כדאמרי
במערבא, Amar Ravina k'd'amri b'maarava, like they say in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. כל מקום שאתה מוצא שני כללות הסמוכים זה לזה, Kol makom
she'atah motzei shnei klalos hasmouchin zeh lazeh, if you ever see two
כללות klalos right next to each other, and again that's how we're
interpreting המצא תמצא, himatzei timatzei, הטל פרט ביניהם. hatel prat beineihem. So
you know, use them to make a כלל פרט klal prat וכלל.
Here you've got two good כלל words, המצא תמצא, himatzei timatzei, here
you've got a lot of פרט words. Excellent. Let's put these פרטים
pratim between the כללין klallin and we'll use a כלל פרט וכלל.
We got all the ingredients, you know, just gotta organize them in
a different manner. Okay?
So normally the order is what all matters, you know, by these
כלל פרט וכלל, but what are you going to do? So here
this כלל פרט would have left you with animals. Here you have
two כללין klallin and we're going to use these פרטים pratim and
like feed them in between the כללין klallin in order to get
where we need to get. Let's just finish this thought. Okay?
שדי שור בין המצא לתמצא. shadi shor bein himatzei l'timatzei. Put שור
between them. And now we're going to go through what we know
is the level of abstraction that we get from each of these
things. לאסויי מה. la'asuyei mah. What would that include? אי לאתויי בעלי
חיים, Ee l'atuyei ba'alei chayim, it can't be so broad to include
animals. מחיה נפקא. M'chayah nafka. We know that from the word animals.
We already got that. אלא לאתויי דבר שאין בעלי חיים. Ella l'atuyei
davar she-ein ba'alei chayim. It must be including something that's not animals.
So do you recover the line between something that's not...
No no, yeah I know. So what could I tell you? So
anyway, because we already have a list that we know includes animals,
right before we normally started in this direction, שור would have said
קורב לגבי מזבח. karev l'gabei mizbei'ach. This would have said, you know,
I don't know,
בכורה, bechorah, etc, etc. But here somehow we're looking at the whole
list ahead of time. We see חיה chayah is here to include
animals. So now we're going to know that when we feed things
in here, we've got to go beyond what we already have as
one of the פרטים. pratim. It's got to give us something beyond
just animals. I understand the irony that שור is going to be
representative of something that's not animals. Okay. Okay. מה... אי לאתויי בעלי
חיים, Ma... ee l'atuyei ba'alei chayim, מחיה
נפקא. m'chayah nafka. אלא לאתויי דבר שאין בעלי חיים. Ella l'atuyei davar
she-ein ba'alei chayim. It must be that שור is coming to include
even not animals. ודרש הכי. V'darash hachi. מה פרט מפורש, what is
the story about the שור? דבר המיטלטל וגופו ממון. Davar hamitaltel v'gufo
mammon. It's chattel and it has intrinsic value. אף כל דבר המיטלטל
וגופו ממון. Af kol davar hamitaltel v'gufo mammon. Okay. So that's what
you get. That would exclude land, slaves that are connected to land,
and שטרות. shtaros. Okay. Now we've really got a question. What do
you need all the other פרטים pratim for?
Okay. ותו שדי חמור בין המצא לתמצא. V'tu she-di chamor bein himatzei
l'timatzei. Now let's put חמור between those two. לאתויי מאי? L'atuyei mai?
What is that going to include? Right? And now the funny thing
is like, what more do you need to include? You've just included
everything: chattel that has intrinsic value. You've excluded the things that are
normally excluded. What work is left to do? So what's the חמור
going to do when you feed it between those two words? אי
לאתויי דבר שאין בעלי חיים, Ee l'atuyei davar she-ein ba'alei chayim, if
it's to include things that are not animals, משור נפקא. mi-shur nafka.
We already did that work from
שור. אלא לאתויי דבר מסויים. Ella l'atuyei davar mesuyam. To include this
דבר מסויים. davar mesuyam. You might remember the דבר מסויים davar mesuyam
discussion we had yesterday that nobody really knows what it's talking about.
Is it something that was, you know, that has a סימן? siman?
Is it something that's a whole thing as opposed to a half
thing? Anyway, somehow it's coming to include that. Although the funny thing
is like, why wouldn't I have assumed that was included? You know,
maybe I would have needed to exclude a דבר שאינו מסויים. davar
she-eino mesuyam. Anyway, nobody really knows what the דבר מסויים davar mesuyam
thing is. אי הכי, Ee hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara שה למה
לי? seh lamma li? Fine. Fine. You did this דבר מסויים davar
mesuyam thing. Now still, what do you need שה for? אלא... ella,
so now we've got a problem. If you start with this whole
list and you know you're going to start with animals, what more
do you need to expand it? So maybe we can explain one
or two things you need to expand, but after a certain point
it's like there's no work left to be done, and you haven't
explained what you do with this whole list. So אלא, says the
גמרא, Gemara fine, let's try another approach.
ריבה ומיעט וריבה הוא. Riba u-mi'et v'riba hu. כדתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל.
Ki-d'tanna d'vei Rabbi Yishmael. Okay. Remember תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Tanna d'vei
Rabbi Yishmael has this approach as opposed to כלל ופרט וכלל, klal
u-prat u-klal, ריבה מיעט וריבה, riba mi'et v'riba, which basically starts one
step ahead of כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat u-klal. It says if
you have just a general and a specific, you've already had that
level of abstraction, anything similar to the specific thing. If it then
does another general, which he's calling the ריבה, riba, inclusive, as opposed
to כלל, then what that means is we're going to include the
entire universe except for something that is the most dissimilar to the
specific thing. Okay. So let's see how that plays out. כדתנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל. Ki-d'tanna d'vei Rabbi Yishmael. במים במים שתי פעמים. Ba-mayim ba-mayim
shetei pe'amim. It says by the fish. It says, you know, that
it's a kosher fish. It says,
what does it say?
את זה תאכלו מכל אשר במים כל אשר לו סנפיר וקשקשת במים.
Et zeh tochelu mi-kol asher ba-mayim kol asher lo snapir v'kaskeset ba-mayim.
So it says במים במים, ba-mayim ba-mayim, eat anything that's in water.
So now we're not talking about sort of the scope of the
fish, we're talking about the bodies of water that the fish are
in that have these הלכות halachos of requiring the kosher
סימנים. simanim. Okay. So אין זה כלל ופרט, ein zeh klal u-prat,
אלא ריבה ומיעט וריבה. ella riba u-mi'et v'riba. ריבה הכל. Riba ha-kol.
מאי ריבה? Mai riba? ריבה כל מילי. Riba kol millei. What's it
going to include? You start by assuming everything's included. אי הכי, Ee
hachi, כל הני פרטי למה לי? kol hanei pratei lamma li? So
let's not worry about the fish and the water. What do you
need these פרטים pratim for? So now what we're saying is
המצא תמצא himatzei timatzei is ריבוי. ribui. We're including the whole universe.
Okay. And now what we're going to do is we're going to
look at this list not to include more things, because you start
by having everything included. We're going to look at this list to
exclude certain things. Things that are not like this list are going
to be excluded from כפל. kefel. Yes.
So why are we doing this first whole top half if we
already did it all from the bottom half?
Well you've got to ask the opposite question. Why do we start
with the bottom half if this is the part that explicitly is
talking about גנב? ganav I don't know. There were two traditions of
דרשות of כפל kefel on both sets of פסוקים. And we're presenting
both of them. There's not just one authority that says like, the
גמרא Gemara keeps saying, there's this תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tanna d'vei
Rabbi Yishmael, this is this תנא, tanna, this is this תנא. tanna.
You know, it's מדרשי הלכה. midreshei halacha. Some מדרשי הלכה midreshei halacha
learns the scope of כפל kefel. from here and some learns it
from here. I really cannot explain why anybody would go here rather
than look at the פסוקים that directly talk about כפל. kefel. I
don't know the answer to that. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara. says
like this.
Okay. ריבה כל מילי. Riba kol millei. אי הכי, Ee hachi, כל
הני פרטי למה לי? kol hanei pratei lamma li? חד למעוטי קרקע.
Chad l'mi'utei karka. One excludes land. חד למעוטי עבדים, chad l'ma'utei avadim,
this is just like we said, you know, yesterday. One excludes slaves.
וחד למעוטי שטרות, ve-chad l'ma'utei shtaros, one excludes documents. גנבה וחיים, gneiva
ve-chayim, now what we're left with though is this is no longer
a כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat u-klal. This is a ריבוי, riboy,
these are מיעוטים, mi'utim, so you have everything except land, slaves, and
documents. So you got you're left with these two words which before
were functioning as כללים.
klalim. What are you going to do now with these two words?
גנבה וחיים. gneiva ve-chayim. So that's actually going to be a transition,
believe it or not, to the first real halachic סוגיא sugya of
this discussion. Okay, אי הכי, iy hachi, where's the גמרא? Gemara גנבה
וחיים, gneiva ve-chayim, so גנבה וחיים, gneiva ve-chayim, what do the words
גנבה וחיים gneiva ve-chayim do? כרב, kerav, like Rav. דאמר רב, d'amar
rav, אחייה לקרן כעין שגנב, achyia le-keren k'ein she-ganav, bring life to
the principal like the time it was burglarized, it was stolen, it
was burglarized. Meaning we're going to see a case coming up on
the next דף that somebody
burglarized something and then it became the value went down or the
animal got thinner and it's his responsibility to restore it according to
the state it was in, the better state it was in when
it was stolen. So that's the חיים and גנבה gneiva is if
you took a גנבה, gneiva, bring it back alive, meaning restore it
as the way it was when it was stolen.
Right,
correct.
So whatever, within certain ranges, we'll talk about that. Okay,
ולמאן דאמר, u-le-man d'amar, now thank God, okay, so we did this
כלל ופרט down here and maybe then we said a similar thing.
Each one of these פרטים pratim were excluding, you know, קרקע, karka,
עבדים, avadim, or שטרות. shtaros, Here we got really, really lost in
the woods, but at the end of the day we said this
was a כלל, these were a ריבוי, riboy, these were excluding קרקע,
karka, שטרות, shtaros, etc. and we're left with those two words to
do other work. Exclude two?
Can't you do it from one of them to tell both?
No, it's אחייה לקרן כעין שגנב. achyia le-keren k'ein she-ganav. You have
to restore it like the time of the גנבה, gneiva, so both
words are being worked. Restore it to what state to the state
it was when it was stolen. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Now we're going to discuss again back to here
whether these two halves are both טוען טענת גנב to'en ta'anat ganav
or one is a גנב ganav and one is טוען טענת גנב.
to'en ta'anat ganav. ולמאן דאמר חד בגנב וחד בטוען טענת גנב, u-le-man
d'amar chad be-ganav ve-chad be-to'en ta'anat ganav, according to the one that
says that one of the first half down here is about גנב
ganav. himself pays double and that's about claiming it was a
גנב. ganav גנב עצמו נפקא ליה מן אם ימצא הגנב, ganav atzmo
nafka lei min im yimatzei ha-ganav, I'm sorry that's excuse me, למאן
דאמר חד בגנב, le-man d'amar chad be-ganav, yeah, גמרא מה אם ימצא
הגנב, Gemara ma im yimatzei ha-ganav, right? Remember it says אם ימצא
הגנב ישלם שנים. im yimatzei ha-ganav yeshalem shnayim. That's here's how you
know that a גנב ganav pays כפל kefel and the scope of
it. So what's the function of this thing up here? So
מיבעי ליה לכדרבא בר אהילאי, mibaei lei le-chi-draba bar ahilai, like Rava
bar Ahilai. דאמר רבא בר אהילאי, d'amar rava bar ahilai, מאי טעמא
דרב mai ta'ama de-rav דאמר מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים פטור.
d'amar modeh biknas ve-achar kach ba'u edim patur. Everybody knows, right, that
if you admit to a קנס knas you cannot have you don't
have to pay a fine based on your own admission. A קנס
knas is a court-imposed punishment and the same way you cannot get
lashes or death penalty based on your own admission, you can't get
a fine based on your own admission. Okay, that's מודה בקנס פטור.
modeh bi-knas patur. But the debate is if you admitted to a
קנס knas and then witnesses came and said that you were liable,
are you still off the hook? Now obviously that wouldn't work by
other things. If you said you did a sin of lashes or
sin of the death penalty and witnesses came, obviously you would get
the punishment. But
monetary קנס knas is seen according to some as different. Possibly one
of the reasons is that because it's a lighter punishment, maybe the
whole purpose of the monetary fine was to incentivize you to come
forth and admit. So if you did admit you don't have to
pay the fine. Okay, so that's what Rav says. מודה בקנס, modeh
bi-knas, if you admit to the קנס knas even after witnesses came
you remain exempt. Where does he learn that from?
Yeah I'm sorry I said this before, ואחר כך באו עדים. ve-achar
kach ba'u edim.
You admitted to it and then after you've admitted witnesses came. Yeah,
okay, that's what I said. Okay anyway I think that's what I
said. Anyway how do you know that even after the witnesses came
you still remain exempt? דכתיב אם המצא תמצא. d'ichtiv im himatzei timatzei.
אם המצא בעדים תמצא בדיינים. im himatzei be-edim timatzei be-dayanim. אם המצא
תמצא himatzei timatzei? בידו.
If it's found in your hand, right? Meaning you didn't come and
admit, right? Somebody else found it in your hand. It was discovered
בעדים, be-edim, in that case the דיינים dayanim will rule that you're
חייב כפל. chayav kefel. But if it was discovered because of your
own admission, then even if afterwards the עדים edim came, it wasn't
discovered because of the עדים, edim, it was discovered because of you.
So if other people were needed to discover it, that's when you
pay כפל. kefel? If you admitted it, you don't pay כפל. kefel.
And in that case what's the problem why you need המצא תמצא?
himatze timatze, Right, exactly.
פרט למרשיע את עצמו.
prat le-marshia et
atzmo.
That excludes a case of a person that, you know, makes himself
wicked, that declares, you know, that confesses his own sin. Okay, so
that's what we did. So now, of course, the question is why
did you still need שור חמור שה חיים shor chamor seh chayim
etcetera? So המצא תמצא, himatze timatze because you know, once it's saying
it, it throws in the details. But basically, this is גנב ganav
and this פסוק is coming to teach you the idea only if
you did not admit it, if it was only if it was
discovered. So the גמרא Gemara says ולמאן דאמר תרווייהו בטוען טענת גנב,
u'l'man d'amar tarvaihu b'to'en ta'anat ganav, and according to the one that
says both of these are about a גנב ganav somebody who claimed
it was stolen, and this is about a real גנב. ganav Okay,
ולמאן דאמר תרווייהו דהאי המצא תמצא מפיק ליה לגנב עצמו, u'l'man d'amar
tarvaihu d'hai himatze timatze mapik lei l'ganav atzmo, and the המצא תמצא
himatze timatze we learned to teach us the scope of a גנב
ganav himself, what are the things he pays כפל kefel for. מרשיע
את עצמו מנלן? marshi'a et atzmo minalan? Where would he know this
הלכה halacha of רב Rav assuming he would פסקן pasken like רב,
Rav, where would he know this הלכה halacha that if you admitted
it, you would never have to pay כפל? kefel,
מאשר ירשיעון אלהים m'asher yarshi'un elohim because it says that who the
judges, right down here it says, or I didn't have the I
didn't write it in, but אשר ירשיעון ירשיעון אלהים ישלם שנים לרעהו.
asher yarshi'un yarshi'un elohim yeshalem shnayim l'rei'eihu. The one who the judges
find guilty will pay double. So only if the judge made you
a רשע. rasha. If you had already made yourself a רשע rasha
by your own admission, you wouldn't pay כפל. kefel, Okay, ולא המרשיע
את עצמו, v'lo ha'marshi'a et atzmo, not the one who made himself
into a רשע. rasha. Fine. ולמאן דאמר חד לגנב וחד בטוען טענת
גנב דאית ליה המצא תמצא למרשיע את עצמו. u'l'man d'amar chad l'ganav
v'chad b'to'en ta'anat ganav d'it lei himatze timatze l'marshi'a et atzmo. So
if you say this is גנב ganav and this is טוען טענת
גנב to'en ta'anat ganav and המצא תמצא himatze timatze tells you you
only pay כפל kefel. if you were
discovered, not if you admitted it. האי אשר ירשיעון מאי דרש ליה?
hai asher yarshi'un mai darash lei? What does he do with אשר
ירשיעון אלהים asher yarshi'un elohim down here? So אמר לך, amar lach,
he'll tell you ההוא מבעי ליה למודה בקנס דפטור. hahu mibaye lei
l'modeh b'knas d'patur. Okay, no, he says look, you can't jump to
say that you're exempt after even after witnesses come before you tell
me the first principle that you cannot be found guilty based on
your own admission. Right? First you have to tell me that if
you admit, we're not going to make you pay based on your
own admission, and then you have to tell me and you even
are exempt even after witnesses come. It's a two-stage, right? You can't
jump to the biggest חידוש. chidush. So he says אשר ירשיעון אלהים
asher yarshi'un elohim says your own admission does not make you pay
כפל, kefel, and המצא תמצא himatze timatze means not only does it
not make you pay כפל, kefel you'll be exempt even after the
witnesses come. All right? So that's what we get out of this.
Everybody following all of this somewhat? Okay, ולמאן דאמר תרווייהו בטוען טענת
גנב u'l'man d'amar tarvaihu b'to'en ta'anat ganav and the one that says
both of these are about טוען טענת גנב to'en ta'anat ganav and
המצא תמצא himatze timatze is about the scope that a גנב ganav
pays כפל. kefel. So קסבר מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים חייב.
kasavar modeh b'knas v'achar kach ba'u edim chayav. Fine. Maybe he'll hold
that only the first stage of that, that your own admission you're
פטור, patur, but if the witnesses come after it maybe you would
be חייב. chayav. Fine. All right. ולמאן דאמר חד לגנב וחד בטוען
טענת גנב דנפקא ליה גנב מהתם. u'l'man d'amar chad l'ganav v'chad b'to'en
ta'anat ganav d'nafka lei ganav m'hatam. If you say that this is
גנב ganav and this is טוען טענת גנב. to'en ta'anat ganav. בשלמא
המצא תמצא bishlama himatze timatze and then we said what do you
need this whole פרשה parsha up here about גנב ganav if you
already have גנב ganav here? So he said well, המצא תמצא himatze
timatze is coming to tell you that even after you admit it
you remain exempt, only if you were never admitted are you חייב
כפל. chayav kefel. So then what do you need the rest of
the פסוק for? What do you need שור חמור ושה חיים? shor
chamor v'seh chayim? Okay, so המצא תמצא himatze timatze לדרב בר אידי,
l'd'rav bar idi, אבל כל הני פרטי למה לי? aval kol hanei
pratei lama li? Why do you need all those details? Because you
basically have גנב ganav from here. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
כדתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, k'd'tana d'vei rabbi yishmael, like what the דבי
רבי ישמעאל d'vei rabbi yishmael teaches. דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל כל פרשה
שנאמרה ונשנית לא נשנית אלא בשביל דבר שנתחדש בה. d'tana d'vei rabbi
yishmael kol parsha she'ne'emra v'nishnit lo nishnit ela bishvil davar she'nitchadesh bah.
Any פרשה parsha that was said once and repeated, it was basically
repeated for like one חידוש, chidush, and you don't have to say
every single word in the second פרשה parsha is meaningful. So המצא
תמצא himatzei timatzei, was the חידוש chidush here that only if you
never admitted, the rest of these details you don't have to worry
about what they're teaching, they were just, you know, once we're saying
it over we're going to say over it with the details. Okay,
now, last question with this. ואימא, v'eima, why don't I say גנב
עצמו בשבועה? ganav atzmo b'shvu'a? Maybe a גנב ganav who pays כפל,
kefel, maybe he only pays it with a שבועה shvu'a the same
way a person who claims that there was a גנב ganav, only
pays כפל kefel. with a שבועה? shvu'a? לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka
datach. That doesn't make sense. דרבי יעקב אומר, d'rabbi yaakov omer, רבי
יעקב rabbi yaakov says שנים ישלם, you pay double. חיים שנים ישלם.
שלא בשבועה, she'lo b'shvu'a, it means you pay it straight away even
all you did was you did a גניבה geneivah, and it says
you pay double even without a שבועה. shvu'a. אתמהה שלא בשבועה? atmeha
she'lo b'shvu'a? You say without a שבועה? shvu'a? אינו אלא בשבועה? eino
ela b'shvu'a? Maybe it's with a שבועה? shvu'a? אמרת לאו כך היא.
amarta lav kach hi. That doesn't make sense. מאי לאו כך היא?
mai lav kach hi? What do you mean that can't be? אמר
אביי, amar abaye, לא לכתוב רחמנא שנים ישלם בגנב ותיתי בקל וחומר
מטוען טענת גנב. lo lichtov rachmana shnayim yeshalem b'ganav v'teiti b'kal vachomer
m'to'en ta'anat ganav. If all if you need the שבועה, shvu'a, then
you wouldn't need the תורה Torah to ever tell you that a
גנב ganav pays כפל. kefel. Since a guy who claims that it
was a גניבה geneivah. and takes a שבועה shvu'a makes כפל, kefel,
you could certainly figure out that a גנב ganav who took a
שבועה shvu'a would pay כפל. kefel. ומה טוען טענת גנב, u'mah to'en
ta'anat ganav, what's about the guy who... If he's שלם הגנב shaleim
hganav or if he's בקל וחומר bekal vachomer מטענת גנב. mi'taanat ganav.
If also, if you need a שבועה, shavua, then you wouldn't need
the Torah to ever tell you that a גנב ganav pays כפל.
kefel. Since the guy who claims that it was a גניבה and
takes a שבועה shavua makes כפל, kefel, you could certainly figure out
that a גנב ganav who took a שבועה shavua would pay כפל.
kefel? ומה טוען טענת גנב, Umah toen taanat ganav, what's about the
guy who just claims that it was a גניבה? דבתחילה מסר לידיה,
D'vatchila masar l'yadei, the object was given to his hands legitimately. He
started as a שומר. shomer, אמר קרא לשלם תרי, Amar kra l'shaleim
trei, that person pays double. גנב עצמו, Ganav atzmo, a real גנב,
ganav דבאיסורא אתא לידיה d'be'issura ata l'yadei that he took it initially
by violating from the very outset, לא כל שכן, lo kol shekein,
of course he would do it. So if you, if you think
that a גנב ganav needs to make a שבועה, shvuah, the תורה
doesn't have to tell me that a גנב ganav pays כפל. kefel.
Right? If a guy who didn't really steal it, started as a
שומר, shomer with a שבועה shvuah pays כפל, kefel? of course a
גנב ganav with a שבועה shvuah *shvuah* pays כפל. kefel אלא שנים
שם דכתב רחמנא בגנב עצמו למה לי? Ella shnaim sham d'chasav rachmana
b'ganav atzmo l'mah li? So why does it have to tell me
a גנב ganav pays כפל? kefel. On my own, just using logic,
I could have figured out a גנב ganav with a שבועה shvuah.
pays כפל. khefel So why would it have to tell me a
גנב ganav. pays כפל? Khefel דאפילו שלא בשבועה, D'afilu shelo b'shvuah, to
tell me a גנב ganav pays כפל even without a שבועה. shvuah,
Okay. By the way, I would say, you could make an opposite
argument. You could say that if I give you it and then
you lie and you take a שבועה, shvuah there's a violation of
trust that exists beyond the violation that's done by a גנב ganav
himself. A גנב ganav himself who steals and then lies and whatever,
I never trusted him, he never betrayed me. Okay, so in theory
you could make an argument that a שומר shomer? who makes a
שבועה shvuah. false, maybe is, is worse. But anyway, that's certainly not
what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay. והאי אם המצא להכי הוא דאתא,
V'hai im himatzei l'hachi hu d'ata, one minute, is this what המצא
himatzei is doing? המי בעי ליה לכדתניא, Hami ba'ei lei l'khadetanya, we
need it what we teach in a ברייתא, that המצא is not
coming for כלל פרט וכלל, or not coming for מודה בקנס פטור.
modeh b'knas patur. It's coming for another הלכה. halacha. ידו. Yado. אין
לי אלא ידו. Ein li ella yado. It says המצא תמצא בידו
הגניבה. himatzei timatzei b'yado hagneiva. So בידו in his hands means you're
not considered a גנב ganav until you take possession of it. Okay,
so if I see your object and I don't know, like, you
know, I hold onto it, like but I haven't actually, you know,
dragged it or done anything, I grabbed it with the desire but
I haven't yet done an act of taking possession, I'm not yet
a גנב. ganav And normally what we assume is that a גנב
ganav, has to do a מעשה קניין. maaseh kinyan. The same act
of taking possession that would be true if I were, if I
were willingly selling you the object, משיכה, meshicha, הגבהה, hagba'ah, etc., until
you do that act, you are not yet a גנב ganav to
be seen as actually taking it for yourself. Now it starts from
the word ידו, yado, it's in your hands. אין לי אלא ידו
גגו חצירו וקפיפו מניין? Ein li ella yado, gago chatzeiro v'kapifo minayin?
How do I know you're a גנב ganav even if it was
just brought into your yard or maybe you brought it into your
yard and then with the intention of stealing it? תלמוד לומר אם
המצא תמצא מכל מקום. Talmud lomar im himatzei timatzei mikol makom. If
it is found in any ways in your hands, meaning it is
in any ways under your possession, not only literally in your hands.
Okay. אם כן לימא קרא או המצא המצא או תמצא תמצא. Im
kein leima kra o himatzei himatzei o timatzei timatzei. So anyway, if
you need it for that, how do you come to use it
for this כלל ופרט or how do you come to use it
for this, I mean this ריבוי ribui or this idea of מודה
בקנס פטור? modeh b'knas patur? No. אם כן, Im kein, if that
was true, if all you wanted to teach me was the הלכה
halacha that it didn't have to literally be in your hands, לימא
קרא או המצא המצא או תמצא תמצא, leima kra o himatzei himatzei
o timatzei timatzei, use the same words. מדשני קרא, Midshani kra, since
it says המצא תמצא, which is calling as the פסוק changed things,
of course that is the exact classic way of articulating using a
double verb, but anyway, שמע מינא תרתי. shma mina tarti. You learn
both הלכות, halachas, that it's even if it's not literally in your
hand and even the הלכה halacha that the scope of things you're
חייב chayav in for גניבה, or another way of saying it is
the הלכה halacha of מודה בקנס פטור או כחפו עדים. modeh b'knas
patur o kachpo eidim. So that was two דפים that was a
lot of מדרש הלכה. Midrash Halacha. And the upshot of all of
that is, is that you're חייב chayav by גניבה for everything that's
chattel and that's intrinsic value. You're exempt for land, slaves, and שטרות,
and this weird דבר המסוים davar hamsuyam that nobody knows what it
is. And the other thing that we basically have seen is this
הלכה halacha of טוען טענת גנב to'ein ta'anas ganav that comes with
a שבועה. shvuah, You claim גניבה. If you claim אבידה aveidah it
wouldn't be true. You claim גניבה and you made a שבועה, then
you pay כפל. Okay, that's the other. And the third thing which
we just said is this הלכה halacha about if it has to
be, what's considered that you're a גנב ganav's when you take it
in your possession, which is not limited to literally being in your
hands. Now let's because תשעה באב is coming up and we have
all other 20 minutes, let's actually get a little bit ahead. And
the גמרא Gemara now is going to go back to what it
learned from חיים הגניבה בחיים. Chayam hagneiva b'chayim. The idea of restoring
גניבה to the point of when you took possession of it. Okay,
so if everybody's game for this, let's try to go a little
bit, get a little bit further. גופא. Gufa. Now this is where
anybody who learns מרובה Meruba when they learn it in ישיבה, yeshiva,
מרובה Meruba. starts on דף ס"ח. daf samech cheis. For the ישיבה,
yeshiva, it does not start on דף ס"ב daf samech beis or
ס"ג. samech gimmel. Okay, גופא. gufa. אמר רב, Amar Rav, קרן כעין
שגנב. keren ke'ein sheganav. I think the only thing that in the
ישיבה yeshiva they like let some learn אגדתא aggadata is learning מדרש
הלכה. Midrash Halacha. What is all this, just history or something? Yeah,
up until now and then we start over here. Right, I'm sure.
Did anybody ever really do it on their own? I mean we
must have, I have it marked up here, so at some point
you actually wind up doing it on your own. Okay, גופא. gufa.
אמר רב, Amar Rav, קרן כעין שגנב, keren ke'ein sheganav, תשלומי כפל
תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה כשעת העמדה בדין. tashlumei kefel tashlumei arba v'chamisha k'sha'as
ha'amada badin. Now here becomes a really I mean I don't know,
really interesting, really... Now here becomes a really, I mean I don't
know, really interesting, really interesting for me because I learned מרובה. Hopefully
I can make it somewhat interesting for you. Anyway, you steal something,
there look, here's the interesting point, okay? There's a moment in time
that you steal the object. This is שעת הגניבה. sha'at hagneivah. I'll
try to use a better pen. שעת הגניבה. sha'at hagneivah. Okay. And
then here you stole the object. And then you finally were caught
and here whatever it's העמדה בדין. ha'amadah badin. You stand, you know
there's the court case that comes, this is January 1 and I
don't know this is December 1. Finally you're caught and you have
to stand case. Now the object changes value between the two times.
Either the animal gets fatter or thinner or the market's value changes
and so on. When you pay two, when there's three things to
be paid here: the principal, the double, and the four and five
times. If we're talking about four and five. Okay. Are the payments
made based on its value when you stole it or based on
its value when you're standing in the court case? Okay? So here
by the way let me just tell you a certain type of
an intuitive logic you might want to have said, I don't know
if it's the most intuitive but what I might have said is
the קרן keren I would say you always pay based on when
you stole it. I took this object from you, it was worth
a thousand dollars when I took it from you, I owe you
a thousand dollars. The fines, and there are two sets of fines:
the כפל and the ארבעה וחמישה, arba'ah v'chamishah, that becomes, remember we
talked about fines being a court imposed punishment, right? If I admit
to it I don't pay. The court creates the obligation, the court
imposes the punishment. So I might say, if the court is making
me pay the fines, I could see going either way. The court
could say pay double, four and five times based on what it
was when you stole it, or pay two to two, four, five
times based on its value right now. Okay, so I could sort
of see but either way I could see that the fines would
go here. And of course the amount that I would pay for
the principal would be the amount it was when I stole it.
רב Rav says an interesting split. Here's what רב Rav says. אמר
רב: Amar Rav: קרן keren כעין, oh no he doesn't say, he
says exactly what I just said. Look at that. Okay. קרן כעין
שגנב. Keren ke'ein sheganav, The principal is based on on what it
was when you stole it, because you're paying back for your act
of stealing and that's what it was when you stole it. That's
how much it was worth. כפל ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה, v'tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah,
the double and the four and five, which is a fine imposed
by the court, that's כשעת העמדה בדין. k'sha'at ha'amadah badin. That's assessed
at the time you stand in the court. Now according to רב's
Rav's statement, he makes it very generically. It could be whether the
object goes up or down in value. Right? It could be here
it was worth a hundred and here it was worth two hundred.
And the principal would be a hundred and the two and the
four and the five times would be based on the two hundred
value because right now we're assessing those fines and we're talking about
what is it worth now. It could be the reverse. Here it's
two hundred, here it's one hundred. Right? It could always be this
is for the act of גניבה, this is for the court imposed
punishment. This goes when you steal it, this goes when it's העמדה
בדין. ha'amadah badin. It kind of makes a lot of sense. Okay.
But now the גמרא Gemara deals with a lot of permutations that
complicate it. So let's take a look at let's do that. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא says like
this. מאי טעמא דרב? Mai ta'ama d'Rav? What's the reasoning of רב?
Rav? אמר קרא: Amar kra: גניבה וחיים. gneivah v'chayim. That's where we
left off. Right, הכי גניבה וחיים. ha'gneivah chayim. Okay. אמאי קאמר רחמנא
חיים וגניבה? Amai ka'amar Rachmana chayim v'gneivah? Why say the word חיים
by גניבה? אחייה לקרן כעין שגנב. Achayei l'keren k'ein sheganav. Bring life
to the principal like it was stolen. So if it was stolen
a certain value, that's the value you have to restore. Now by
the way there's a big תוספות Tosafot here and there's a fascinating
question that sort of absorbs the ראשונים Rishonim which is the fact
that it says אחייה לקרן כעין שגנב achayei l'keren k'ein sheganav makes
it sound like it's a special הלכה halacha by גניבה. But actually
it's the same הלכה halacha by גזילה, gezeilah, at least it seems
to be. If I steal something from you and not גניבה, I
didn't burgle it. Okay? I robbed you at gunpoint and I took
something from you, I hijacked your car. Okay? So how much would
I pay? And then it got crashed or whatever the value went
up value went down. I pay based on what it was when
I stole it. That was the act of transgression or that was
the act of liability, that's how you assess the value. So it
could be that the הלכה halacha that the קרן keren is based
on the time it was stolen or גניבה, גזילה, gezeilah, whatever, that's
not the חידוש chidush of רב. Rav. Obviously you pay based on
when the act was done. That was when you suffer that was
when you when you incurred liability. The חידוש chidush is that the
fines go by not that time but by the time that you
stand in court. Okay? But anyway this big תוספות Tosafot is trying
to figure out whether גזילה gezeilah is different than גניבה. All right
so the גמרא says like this. אחייה לקרן כעין שגנב. Achayei l'keren
k'ein sheganav. So אמר רב ששת: Amar Rav Sheshet: אמינא, Amina, I
said כי ניים. ki nayim. Rav must have been dozing off when
he said that. He didn't know what he was talking about. דתניא
*detanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *braita*, כחושה והשמינה משלם תשלומי כפל
ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה arba'ah vachamisha, כעין שגנב *kechushah vehishminah meshallem tashlumei kefel
vetashlumei arba'ah vachamishah ke-ein sheganav*. If it was thin and you fattened
it, then you're going to pay the כפל *kefel*, the two and
the four and the five, not based on its greater value now
when you're standing in court as I've, you know, I've been feeding
your cow for this last year, so now it's worth twice as
much, so I'm going to pay a bigger fine because I've been
feeding it? So there it says you pay the two and the
four and the five not based on its value and the time
of the court, but based on its original value. משלם תשלומי כפל
ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה arba'ah vachamisha כעין שגנב *meshallem tashlumei kefel vetashlumei arba'ah
vachamishah ke-ein sheganav*. So it's not like רב Rav *Rav* says. It's
not like when it's at the time of the court. גמרא *Gemara*
says, wait a minute, that's a special case. That didn't just go
up in value, you increased the value. אמרי משום דאמר ליה *amrei
mishum de-amar leh* because the גנב ganav *ganav* can say to the
owner, אנא פטימנא ואת שקלת *ana patimna ve-at shaklat*, I fattened it
and you're going to benefit? Yeah, poor גנב ganav *ganav*. My heart
really goes out to him. But anyway, the גמרא *Gemara* says that
that would be different. An increase in value that is due to
the גנב ganav, *ganav* is not part of what we assess in
terms of the value of the object. Yes, we make you pay
two and four and five based on what its value is right
now, but we don't look at value that is due to what
the גנב *ganav* contributed. Like that is not seen as the thing
he took from you. If it went up in value on its
own, if the market went up in value, then it's the thing
he took from you and we'll make him pay two or four
and five based on this time. But if it's value that he
added, he's not going to pay two and four and five onto
the value that he added, which makes a lot of sense. All
right, בשינוי *beshinnui*. Yeah, בשינוי *beshinnui* would mean that he's קונה koneh
*koneh* it. This is more that that addition isn't yours. The whole
object might be yours, it's not like he's קונה koneh *koneh* with
שינוי shinui *shinnui*, but the addition isn't yours, so he's not going
to pay on the addition. Yeah, like if he bought a house
and then he made a like, you know, he went to a,
I don't know, he stole a car and then he got a
paint job on it and he added a tape deck and all
those types of things, he shouldn't be paying based on what he
added to the car, right? What'd you say? I said tape deck.
Yeah, whatever, sound system. I'm a little dated. A little dated, yes.
And it begs the question of what happens if the value decreases
because he neglects it. So we're going to get to that. Okay,
just to get, no, you mean does he get a break because,
you know, now you neglected it and we're going to give you
a break as a result of that? Right, so let's take a
look. Ironically, the answer might be yes. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this, okay, okay, תא שמע שמנה והכחישה *ta shema shmenah vehich-hishah*.
Here you go, exactly Jonathan's case. It started off as fat and
he weakened it, he thinned it out. Okay, he put it on
a diet, exercise. Okay, משלם תשלומי כפל ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה כעין שגנב
*meshallem tashlumei kefel vetashlumei arba'ah vachamishah ke-ein sheganav*. Same thing. It goes
like כעין שגנב *ke-ein sheganav*. Okay, now there you would say, now
there actually though it does make sense, right? Because there you could
say, right, let's see what the גמרא *Gemara* says. According to רב
Rav *Rav*, what are we going to pay two and four and
five based on העמדה בדין *ha'amadah badin*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says
התם נמי משום דאמרינן ליה *hatam nami mishum de-amrinan leh* because you
say to him מה לי כולא קטלה מה לי פלגא קטלה *mah
li kullah katlah mah li palga katlah*. What difference does it make
if you killed it halfway or you killed it the whole way?
Now what does that mean? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* like have a whole complicated explanation. רש"י *Rashi* says, well, if
we're talking about four and five, so one of the scenarios of
four and five is slaughtering it. So if you start beating it,
it's like beginning the process of slaughtering it. And that's why we
consider that the העמדה בדין *ha'amadah badin* is when you started beating
it and weakening it, which is like what? Like first of all,
that doesn't address the כפל *kefel* case. Second of all, that doesn't
address the four and five case when you sell it. Third of
all, beating it is not beginning a process of slaughtering it. If
you were to kill it without slaughtering it, you wouldn't pay four
and five. So what does any of that mean? So תוספות Tosfot
*Tosafot* says, and maybe a little bit more along your lines, תוספות
*Tosafot* says, well, if you had killed it, you would have been
קונה koneh. *koneh* it with a שינוי shinui. *shinnui*. So when you
beat it, it's sort of like that. What does it mean it's
sort of like that? You're still not קונה koneh. *koneh* with שינוי
*shinnui*, you just got it thinner. So I think it's actually Jonathan's
point. I think it's the reverse. The same way I'm not going
to have to pay four and five for a value that I
added, if I actually took away value, I shouldn't get off the
hook, right? It was worth a thousand. I made it worth five
hundred. So I'm only going to have to pay four and five
for five hundred? I stole that value, the reason it was worth
less was because I took that value away. That shouldn't get me
off the hook from paying my two and four and five based
on that. Okay, so any value that I added or any value
that I took away, right, is not going to factor into the
two and four and five computation here. When we say you go
by here, it's when the value changes by itself. But if you
increase the value, you're not going to suffer as a result of
that, and if you decrease the value, you're not going to be
rewarded as a result of that. Okay, so in those cases we'll
go back to the original שעת הגניבה *sha'at hagneivah*, to the original
שעת הגניבה *sha'at hagneivah*, yes. I understand. Yeah, but that's at least,
that's what the גמרא's saying. You didn't have to come to this
conclusion, but right, the גמרא's at least saying that you're already being
penalized by the ארבעה וחמישה, we're not going to add that ארבעה
וחמישה onto a value that you added, right? Okay, so if you
added the value or took value away, you're not going to either
lose or benefit as a result of that. So anyway, כי קאמר
רב ביוקרא וזולא. Ki ka'amar Rav beyokra vezula. But what was רב
talking about when the market prices went up and down? Now תוספות
points out what you could also have said is, the animal got
fatter or thinner on its own, not because of any act that
I did, okay? But the point is any act that I did,
I will not benefit or lose as a result of it, okay?
But when רב says that you're going to go by this value,
it's going to be when the market values naturally go up or
down. Okay, so let's keep with that in mind, let's go further.
ביוקרא וזולא. Beyokra vezula.
והאמר הוא דקאמר. Veha'am hu deka'amar. So גמרא says, היכי דמי? Heichi
dami? Alright, let's figure this out. Market values changing. What's the case?
אילימא דמעיקרא שויא זוזא ולבסוף שויא ארבע, Ilei'ima demikara shavya zuza uvesof
shavya arba, originally was worth one and then it was worth four,
so ארבע זוזי. arba zuzei. קרן כעין שגנב, Keren ke'ein sheganav, so
you're going to tell me you're only going to pay the principal,
you're only going to pay one, because that's what it was when
you stole it. בת לימא פליגי דרבא אדרבא? Bat leima paligi deRava
adeRaba? So we say this argues on רבא Rava on רבא? Rava?
דאמר רבא: De'amar Rava: האי מאן דגזל חביתא דחמרא דחבריה. Hai man
degazal chavita dechamar dechavreih. You stole a barrel of wine from your
friend. מעיקרא שויא זוזא, Meikara shavya zuza, originally was worth one זוז,
zuz, ולבסוף שויא ארבע זוזי, uvesof shavya arba zuzei, and then it
was worth four. תברה שעת, Tavrah shat, if you yourself, when it
was at the higher value, destroyed it, you broke it, you spilled
it, or you drank it, whatever you did to it, right? משלם
ארבע, Meshalem arba, you pay four. אתבר ממילא, Itbar mimeila, if it
broke on its own, משלם זוזא, Meshalem zuza, you pay one. So
tell me why is that? You stole a barrel of wine worth
one, now it's worth four. If it breaks, you still pay- you
pay one, that's what it was worth when you stole it. But
if you drank it, you pay four. Why should that be? Because
when you drink it now, or you actively destroy it or drink
it, you are doing another act of liability, right? I stole from
you it was worth one, but now, if I'm going to drink
it, I'm further stealing, destroying your object, and now it's an object
that's worth four. So forget the גניבה, you're going to tell to
me pretend you never stole it. You had my barrel of wine
by you and you broke it or you drank it, it was
worth four when you broke it or drank it, I'm going to
forget about the stealing, pay the four, you know, pay based on
that. So therefore, if you actively destroy it when it's worth more,
you're incurring an additional liability. Okay, so when we say קרן כעין
שגנב, Keren k'ein sheganav. it was worth one and four, and then
four, and then we say pay the one, that would only be
in a case of what? When you did not actively destroy it.
But if you actively destroyed it later on, you'd actually pay the
higher value even for the principal. Also because it moves from one
רשות reshut to another at that moment, right? You're קונה koneh, it.
Yeah, it could be that you're קונה it, but like, I'm trying
to think about cases- I don't think it's limited to being קונה.
I think it's that you did an act- another act of מזיק
mazik and גניבה. I'm trying to think about a scenario where you
could do an act of מזיק mazik without being קונה. Like I
could imagine that you, let's say you defaced it in a way
that you wouldn't say שינוי קונה, shinui koneh, but in a way
that sort of that made- you know, that- that seriously, you know,
depreciated its value. But שינוי קונה shinui koneh is when you- when
you make a desk out of a piece of wood. Right. So
that- so in that case, if you steal a piece of wood,
the desk is yours. Right. But I'm just saying I don't see
that this is limited to the fact that you own it. What
it is primarily about is that you did another act of- of
incurring liability. Right. If I destroyed it, you know, let's say I
don't know, I had your, you know, your Van Gogh painting or
whatever, and I, you know, you know, did some mark on it
that technically would not be a שינוי that would make me קונה,
but now made it worth a, you know, not 100 million dollars
anymore, right? So it's merely that you did another act of damage,
not so much that you did a שינוי. Yes. So then how
would like negligence fit into this? Ah, so that's exactly the חידוש.
chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is- is that, and this is a good
question, right? A גנב or גזלן, gazlan, are they like a שומר?
shomer What is their liability in terms of negligence? And here it's
a little bit, I don't know if it's ironic, it could play
out ironically. If I'm a שומר shomer of your object and you
gave it to me when it was worth one, and then it
was worth four, and then it got damaged due to my negligence,
how much do you think I pay? What do you think I
should pay? Just intuitively, what would you say? Four. It was worth
four, I was חייב chayav to be שומר shomer. it, I was
negligent, and a- an object worth four was destroyed that I had,
it doesn't matter that I got it at one, at the time
it was worth four I had responsibility, I was negligent, I pay,
I pay four. But if a גנב, and that's exactly what this
is being said here, steals it, and it was destroyed אתבר ממילא,
itbar mimeila, even due to negligence, he only pays one. You know
why? Because he never accepted... accepted the obligations of שמירה. shmira. So
his payment is only for the original act of stealing, okay, or
for another act of damage or whatever. His payment is not as
a שומר. shomer All right. I wouldn't -- I don't understand why
we would say he accepts the obligations if he didn't take it.
So what we basically say is he's already obligated to pay as
soon as he stole it. So here's the flip side of it.
Let's say it breaks due to an אונס. oness. If you're a
שומר shomer and it breaks due to an אונס, oness, do you
pay? No. If you're a גנב and it breaks due to an
אונס, oness, do you pay? Yes. Because you're not paying because of
your negligence, you're paying because you stole it. So the liability focuses
-- the original point. Right, exactly. So it's a different focus on
why are you paying. A שומר shomer's is paying because of negligence
and damage, and the גנב is paying because of the act of
stealing. So the שומר's shomer, liability focuses on when the damage occurred,
the גנב's on the original act. But in this case, when you
actively broke it, it's a new act of liability. It's not a
חיוב as a שומר, shomer, it's a new act of liability. And
also רש"י says he has to return it. For a גנב you
always have the obligation to return it. Right. So you don't really
fully own it, you have to give it back. It's still the
owner's object. Right, but even as a שומר, shomer. you have no
rights to it as a שומר. shomer You always have this... but
then in that way שומר shomer and גנב are the same, it's
not yours and you have to return it. But you could be
using it. As a שומר shomer you don't have the permission to
be using it. No, only as a שוכר socher or שואל. shoel.
As a שומר you just have to protect it and give it
back. Okay, so the גמרא says, ah, so תוספות argues on רבא
Rava because רבא Rava says that there'll be times when you pay
the later value for the קרן keren if you actually actively destroyed
it. So the גמרא says, no, אמרי כי אמר רבא כגון דמעיקרא
שויא ארבע ולבסוף שויא זוזא. Amri ki amar Rava kegon d'meikara shavei
arba u'levasof shavei zuza. Now, of course, it would have been nicer
to say that רבא Rava is talking about it just broke by
itself, okay, but the גמרא switches it to the case, says it
specifically went down in value. It started as four and ended as
one. What probably has to say that because רבא Rava is also
talking about when you slaughtered it or you sold it. So there
you did actively destroy it. So in that case, if you slaughtered
it and it was worth more, you'd pay the higher value. So
when does רבא Rava say you pay the original value? If it
now is worth less, okay? קרן keren כעין שגנב. So it started
by -- if it's worth one and here it's worth four, so
the קרן keren is -- I'm sorry, the opposite. Here it's worth
four and here it's worth one. So you pay back the קרן
keren like you stole it because that was the act that you
incurred the liability for the principal. קרן כעין שגנב תשלומי כפל ותשלומי
ארבעה וחמישה כשעת עמדה בדין. Keren k'ein sheganav tashlumei kefel v'tashlumei arba'ah
v'chamishah k'sha'at amda badin. And you pay the two and the four
and the five based on this because that's when the court is
imposing the payment and that's how it's worth -- how much it's
worth right now. In the reverse case, if it were presumably, if
it were one and four, okay, and you did not שחט shachat
it, it was not a case of slaughtering it, it just was
around or it broke by itself, presumably in that case we would
say yes, you pay קרן keren this and four and five and
two -- well not whatever, if you assume you didn't slaughter it,
you would pay based on the higher value. Right, presumably the גמרא
doesn't have a problem with saying that the two and the four
and the five are go by the higher value. They only had
a problem that in this case the קרן keren. should also go
by the higher value. Okay, so we've basically established it. Anything that
you actively have increased or decreased the value as a גנב, you're
not going to benefit or lose as a result of. If the
value changes by itself, the -- this is the liability for stealing
it, that's the קרן. This is when the court imposes it, this
is the four and the five. And the only possible difference is
that if you actively destroy it and it's worth more, then you're
going to pay the principal for that higher value as well. Okay,
we will stop with this for now.